BU Records: Baptist Student Union, Inclusive: 1921-1976, undated, Bulk: 1960-1963, undated.
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
BU Records: Baptist Student Union
Inclusive: 1921-1976, undated, Bulk: 1960-1963, undated.
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
BU/15
Baylor University Baptist Student Union
10 document boxes
BU Records: Baptist Student Union includes correspondence, financial records, literary productions, organizational records and photographs of the ministries and events put on by the organization between 1930-1960.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
The Baptist Student Union (BSU) was a national organization with branches at college campuses across the country. It was created out of a need to promote Baptist values, beliefs, and culture among college students. In the early 20th century, there were attempts to address this need through both inter-denominational organizations such as the Young Men’s Christian Academy (Y.M.C.A.) and Baptist groups such as the Baptist Student Mission Movement. The origins of the Baptist Student Union itself can be traced back to what became known as the “Baylor Prayer Covenant”, a pact made by six male students on the campus of Baylor University on 1905 October 21 to pray for an organization that would promote Baptist religion on campus. Appeals for an organization were made to the Baptist General Convention of Texas (BGCT). After consulting with students, the “Baptist Student Union” was formally established by the BGCT at the Palacios Encampment in 1920 July. Early organizations like the Baptist Student Missions Movement were absorbed into the BSU.
Baylor University’s branch of the BSU was founded in 1920. The Baylor BSU branch hosted a variety of events, including student revivals, Focus Week, school retreats, and charity events. The organization also sponsored missionary activity both in the United States as well as abroad. Programs for international students was also an important priority for the BSU. The organization is currently known as Baptist Student Ministries (BSM) and continues to operate on Baylor's campus today.
Scope and Content
BU Records: Baptist Student Union consists of materials from 1921-1967, with the bulk of materials from 1960-1963. The records reflect the work of the Baptist Student Union at Baylor University, an organization centered around promoting Baptist beliefs and culture among students.
Series I. Correspondence consists of correspondence between the BSU Director, members of the executive council members, and those outside of Baylor. Series II. Events consists of materials relating to events and programs organized by the BSU. Series III. Financial Records consists of budgets and financial reports. Series IV. Literary Productions consists of newsletters and programs published by the BSU. Series V. Organization Records consists of materials relating to executive council. Series VI. Photographs contains photographs of BSU events and members.
Arrangement
Prior to processing, this collection was organized within 8 document boxes. The materials were organized roughly by date and subject. For the current round of processing, materials on the same topic were organized together.
Currently, there are six series: Series I. Correspondence, Series II. Events, Series III. Financial Records, Series IV. Literary Productions, Series V. Organizational Records, Series VI. Photographs. The series are arranged alphabetically by subject.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. BU/15. Acquired 0-00-00
Related Resources
Related references
"Baptist Student Ministries Returns to Campus". BaylorNews Online. 2018 February 16th. Accessed 2020 December 14.
Baylor University. 1969. "Appointment of Larry Hodges of Huntsville as director of student religious activities was announced Thursday (May 22).".
Baylor University. 1979. "Baylor's New BSU Directors Outlines Goals and Plans.".
Binford, T.A. “Christian Association at Baylor to Be Baptist Student UnionDLNew Pres.” The Baylor Lariat. 1920 November 20.
Boone, Joseph P. "It Came To Pass: The Birth, Growth, and Evaluation of the Baptist Student Union and the Baptist Chairs of Bible." Ann Arbor, Michigan: Edwards Brothers, Inc., 1953.
Cox, Marc. “BSU director says job is ‘a new start’ for Baylor. The Lariat, 1993 September 28.
Leavell, Frank H. "The Baptist Student Union." Nashville, Tennessee: Sunday School Board of the Southern Baptist Convention, 1927.
McBeth, Harry Leon. "Texas Baptists: A Sesquicentennial History." Dallas, Texas: Baptistway Press, 1998.
"The campus...". The Lariat. 1972 April 26.
"Vanns to Direct Literary Clinic Here Saturday". The Baylor Lariat. 1968 October 10.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Baptist General Convention of Texas.; Baylor University -- Societies, etc.; Baylor University -- Students.
Subjects
Baptist associations -- Texas -- Waco.; Baptist universities and colleges -- Texas -- Waco.; Baptists -- Education (Higher) -- United States.; Baptists -- Texas -- McLennan County -- History.; Baptists -- Texas -- Waco.; Business correspondence.; Christian universities and colleges -- Texas -- Societies, etc.; Financial records.; Newsletters.; Personal correspondence.; Photographs.; Programs (Publications).; Records (Documents); Waco (Tex.) -- Church history.
- Correspondence, 1959-1963, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  This series contains correspondence related to the BSU director, executive council, and organization events. This series is in good condition.
  - Billy Graham Day, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - BSU, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Executive Council, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Focus Week, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - General Correspondence (1 of 2), 1962 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - General Correspondence (2 of 2), 1962 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Jim Bailey, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Joan Geiger, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - M.B. Carroll, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Pre-School Retreat, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Raymond Vickery, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Roy Harrell Personal Correspondence (1of 6), 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Roy Harrell Personal Correspondence (2 of 6), 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Roy Harrell Personal Correspondence (3 of 6), 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Roy Harrell Personal Correspondence (4 of 6), 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Roy Harrell Personal Correspondence (5 of 6), 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Roy Harrell Personal Correspondence (6 of 6), 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - W.F. Howard, Dave Cheavens, Harrell, Students, 1962-1965 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - World Emphasis Week and Latham Springs, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Youth Services, Harles Cone, Louis Cobbs, Youth-Led Revivals, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Events, 1945-1963, undated; 2
  This series contains materials relating to the events, ministries, and programs put on by the BSU. This series is in good condition.
  - Annual Banquet, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Baptist Student Union Convention 1960, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Baptist Student Union Convention 1962, 1959-1962 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Billy Graham Day — November 14th, 1962, 1962, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - BSU Banquet, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - BRH Choir Summer Tour, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - BSU Convention — Dallas, Abilene, 1949-1954 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - BSU State Convention, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - BSU Lecture Series, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Calendar of Events, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Car Wash 1963 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Campus Revival 1955, 1954-1955 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Focus Week 1943, 1942-1943, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Focus Week 1945 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Focus Week 1947, 1946-1947, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Focus Week 1949, 1948-1952 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Focus Week 1950 (1 of 2), 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Focus Week 1950 (2 of 2), 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Focus Week 1951 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Focus Week 1952 (1 of 2), 1950-1952 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Focus Week 1952 (2 of 2), 1950-1952 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Focus Week 1954, 1953-1954 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Focus Week 1956 (1 of 4), 1954-1957 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Focus Week 1956 (2 of 4), 1954-1957 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Focus Week 1956 (3 of 4), 1954-1957 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Focus Week 1956 (4 of 4), 1954-1957 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Focus Week 1958 (1 of 2), 1956-1958 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Focus Week 1958 (1 of 2), 1956-1958 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Focus Week 1960 (1 of 3), 1960, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Focus Week 1960 (2 of 3), 1960, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Focus Week 1960 (3 of 3), 1960, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Focus Week 1961 (1 of 3), 1960-1961, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Focus Week 1961 (2 of 3), 1960-1961, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Focus Week 1961 (3 of 3), 1960-1961, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Focus Week 1963 (1 of 5), 1961-1963, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Focus Week 1963 (2 of 5), 1961-1963, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Focus Week 1963 (3 of 5), 1961-1963, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Focus Week 1963 (4 of 5), 1961-1963, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Focus Week 1963 (5 of 5), 1961-1963, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Hospital Volunteering, 1959 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - International Student Retreat 1962, 1959-1962 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - International Student Dinner, 1961-1962 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Latham Springs 1945 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Latham Springs 1955 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Missions Summer, 1960, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Minister’s Day 1962 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Pre-School Retreat 1960 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Pre-School Retreat 1961 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Pre-School Retreat 1962, 196-1962, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Religious Emphasis Week 1953 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Ridgecrest Retreat 1954, 1954-1955 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Vision Week, 1962-1963 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Waco Youth for Christ, 1945-1946, undated (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - World Emphasis Week 1961-1962, 1960-1962, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Youth Conference — Baptist World Alliance, 1961-1963 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Financial Records, 1954-1962; 3
  This series contains the budgets and treasurer reports of the Baptist Student Union. This series is in good condition.
  - Budget, 1954-1955 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Budget, 1958-1959 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Budget, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Budget, 1961-1962 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Treasurer Report, 1961-1962 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Treasurer Report — Freshmen BSU Council, 1961-1962 (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Literary Productions, 1942-1976; 4
  The series contains the event programs and newsletters of the Baptist Student Union. This series is in good condition.
  - Focus Week Programs, 1942-1950 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Focus Week Programs, 1952-1957 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - “The Baptist Student”, 1963 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - “The Link” Newsletter, 1958-1959 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - “The Link” Editor — Diane Y., 1959-1960 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Newsletter — Student Department, 1963 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - “The Vision” Vol.1, No.1, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 15)
- Organizational Records, 1921-1964, undated; 5
  This series contains materials relating to the Executive Council and its meetings, the various committees, and other demographics. This series is in good condition.
  - Baptist General Convention of Texas — BSU Transition, 1962-1963 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - BSU Before 1946, 1921-1946 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - BSU Car Wash Committee, 1963 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - BSU On Campus Committee, 1963 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - BSU Council Minutes, 1951-1952 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - BSU Council Minutes, 1960-1961 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - BSU Council Minutes, 1961-1963 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - BSU Executive Council 1962 (1 of 2), 1962-1963 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - BSU Executive Council 1962 (2 of 2), 1962-1963 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - BSU Executive Council Elections 1962, 1962-1963 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - BSU Executive Council Former Members, 1961-1963 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - BSU Executive Council — Member Personal Information, 1961-1963 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - BSU Executive Council Retreat, 1960 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - BSU Executive Council Retreat, 1962-1963 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - BSU Executive Council Retreat, 1963 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - BSU Freshman Council, 1962-1963 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - BSU General Movement (1 of 2), 1957-1964, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - BSU General Movement (2 of 2), 1957-1964, undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - BSU Handbook and Mailings, 1959-1962 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - BSU Missions Committee, 1957-1960 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - BSU Off Campus Committee, 1963 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - BSU President — Billy Rogers, 1959-1960, undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - BSU Promotional Committee, 1963, undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - BSU Reports (1 of 2), 1934-1956, undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - BSU Reports (2 of 2), 1934-1956, undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - BSU Reports (1 of 2), 1961-1962 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - BSU Reports (2 of 2), 1961-1962 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - BSU Speech Choir, 1955, undated (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - BSU Summer Work, 1962 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Calendars, 1960-1962 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Christian Maturity Council, 1961-1962 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Denominational Statistics, 1948 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Evaluation of Baylor BSU (1 of 2), 1955-1960, undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Evaluation of Baylor BSU (2 of 2), 1955-1960, undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Informal Discussion Materials for Presidents (1 of 2), 1962-1964, undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Informal Discussion Materials for Presidents (2 of 2), 1962-1964, undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - International Students, 1962 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - International Students, 1963 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Leadership Lab, 1963 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Monthly Reports — Roy Harrell, 1962-1963 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - “New Life for BSU at Baylor” by James Otis, undated (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Other Denominations, 1961 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Spring Planning Conference, 1955 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Student Recommendations, 1961-1962 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Summer Workers, 1961-1962 (Box 10, Folder 13)
- Photographs, 1949-1959; 6
  This series contains photographs of Baptist Student Union events and members. This series is in good condition.
  - Photographs (1 of 3), 1949 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Photographs (2 of 3), 1949 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Photographs (3 of 3), 1949 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Photographs (1 of 3), 1956 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Photographs (2 of 3), 1956 (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Photographs (3 of 3), 1956 (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Photographs, 1957 (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Photographs, 1959 (Box 10, Folder 21)